Cardiovascular disease happens for a
number of reasons. Damage to the blood
vessel wall, plaque buildup, clots
sticking in the opening, not allowing
blood flow through, plenty of other
examples. One of the factors that seems
to contribute is now getting more
attention is the enzyme mooperoxidase.
In fact, it was first identified almost
three decades ago as being a
cardiovascular risk. But now it's
resurging due to a study recently
released that delves deep into how MO is
manipulated and how it impacts our
arteries. The question is what is it
doing? And if it's bad, how can we shut
it down? Well, in short, MO attacks and
stiffens our arteries. In fact, when we
look at the relationship between blood
mo levels and reduced flow mediated
dilation, so that's a metric of blood
vessel function, the ability for the
blood vessel to open and close normally.
We can see an inverse relationship. The
horizontal axis is greater MO in the
blood. The vertical is the flow median
dilation. The higher the better for your
blood vessel function. Clearly following
the red line, as MO increases, FMD is
reduced. To be clear, this isn't a
strong association, but it is there. And
we do know that MO is only one of many
factors that contribute to reduced FMD
function. And since this is a simple
association, the researchers did further
experiments to point the finger more
directly at MO causing problems in blood
vessel relaxation, increasing blood
vessel stiffness. Okay, but exactly how
is MO causing these diminishments in
blood vessel function, increased blood
vessel stiffness? Well, it has a lot to
do with cells that secrete MO. When
looking at a specific region of the
blood vessel, there's a unique
interaction between three groups of
cells. To clarify, if we were to zoom
into your blood vessel, there's an
initial lining of cells called
endothelial cells. If you've been
watching physionic content at all, you
know that these cells release different
molecules that open and tighten the
blood vessel, regulating blood pressure
and blood vessel health. Under that
layer are structural proteins and below
that are smooth muscle cells, the cells
that actually enact the tightening and
opening of the arteries. Then although
we rarely discuss it, there are fat
cells that surround these vascular
smooth muscle cells. And between the fat
cells are also immune cells. It's these
cells, the immune cells that secrete mo.
And they actually invade into the fat
tissue far more. But why are they just
having a hissy fit because you took away
their game console? I mean, I'd be
upset, too, but enough to start hurting
your neighbors? Unlikely. So, what else
could it be? Well, the fat cells draw
them in by releasing molecules called
chemocines. These chemocines attract
immune cells and then the immune cells
worsen the arterial environment by
releasing MO. Think of it like a sibling
shooting a rubber band behind a parent's
back at their brother. The immune cell
and the immune cell, the brother getting
back because it starts releasing MO or I
don't know throwing a stone at their
sibling in retaliation. The start is at
the fat cell even if the immune cells
get caught and make it worse. And by
making it worse, there is evidence that
the immune cells through MO reprogram
the fat cells to release less of the
beneficial hormones like adypenectin. So
to sum, something that you do, which
we'll get to, increases the invasion of
immune cells into the fat tissue around
your blood vessels. The fat cells
communicate through molecules with your
immune cells and recruit them to the
area. These immune cells then release MO
which increases the inflammatory signals
from the fat cells by for example
reducing the release of a highly
beneficial hormone called adipeneectin.
This reduced release of adipeneectin
along with other molecular changes
stiffens the arteries. Okay. Now, how
can we deinfluence our fat cells around
our blood vessels to allow this immune
invasion? And how can we stifle this MO
release? Well, before that, if you'd be
interested in understanding more on NO's
effects on your blood vessels, like the
direct effects or the relationship to
the fat cells and something that I
actually haven't discussed before,
nitroyine,
along with some more direct nutritional
supplemental means of reducing MO. You
may actually already be using some of
these, in fact. Then check out the
Physionic Insiders. That's where you'll
have access to the full nerdier version
of this video that you're watching, plus
an accompanying article and resources.
Why? Like these. Check it out. The link
to join the insiders is in the
description. I'll see you over there.
But assuming that you despise the idea
of joining the insiders right now
because you want to know how to reduce
mo as is, then buckle in. The main study
that we've been going over is not solely
in animals. as researchers did relate
some of this to humans as well and we
know humans express MO. However, it's
also shown that people who undergo
beriatric surgery as seen here the red
box is those before surgery and the blue
is after experience drops in no levels.
The higher the box the worse. So the
takeaway is simply cut out your stomach.
I'm kidding. Relax. I mean technically
that is a true interpretation but the
greater applicability is that weight
loss correlates with lower MO levels.
And if we open the same data again and
notice the green box that's lean
individuals. Notice how they have even
lower MO levels. Hint hint. So yes, your
weight. And I would take an educated
guess that it's actually your fat mass,
especially visceral fat is a major
determinant of mo levels because
remember this all starts at the fat, the
sister that shoots the rubber band at
the brother, the immune cells. If you
can reduce the siren's call of the fat
to the immune cell, you've already
reduced your risk significantly. But in
addition, that means reduced
inflammation that might otherwise
activate these modding immune cells. And
speaking to that, anti-inflammatory
diets like those rich in antioxidants,
reduce processed foods, and the like
have tremendous impact on all the above.
And a simple experiment that you could
do if you were inclined would be to get
your MO tested. It's available at most
publicly available blood testing
facilities. Change your diet for 3
months, especially if you lose body fat
and visceral fat, and then retest. You'd
likely see a protective decline. All
right, I realize that might have been a
lot to digest. Ultimately, here are a
few key takeaway points. One, the
mechanistic mo or myoparoxidase is
secreted by immune cells once recruited
to the inflammatory fat tissue
surrounding our blood vessels, which
ultimately leads to even more
inflammation and a stiffening of the
blood vessels. Not good. Two, the test.
There are simple MO tests that are
available if you wanted to get yours
checked. This is definitely not
necessary, but if you're curious about
an inflammatory test closer to where the
diseases actually lie, the arteries,
there you go. Three, the fixes. One,
clearly fat and especially visceral fat
loss. This is critical. The less
inflammatory tissue, i.e. visceral fat,
the less MO likely consuming an
anti-inflammatory diet that's rich in
antioxidants and keeps your weight in
check. All important for keeping MO
levels low, as we saw that leaner
individuals naturally just have lower
MO. But speaking to visceral fat and
inflammation, I cover much more on the
topic right here. Thanks for hanging
out. See you.